Guide to the Stanford University, Engineering Case Program, Case Files SC0269
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Engineering Case Program, case files
1948-1972
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Fuchs, H. O. (Henry Otten)
Arnold, John E., 1913-1963
SC0269
3.5 Linear Feet
Scope and Content
The Engineering Case Program, which began at Stanford University in 1964, provided written accounts of engineering problems to be used in the training of engineers. This collection consists of the master files from 114 cases where the author was a Stanford faculty or staff member or the event described happened in the San Francisco Bay Area. In addition to the case description, some files include correspondence, memoranda, diagrams, and photographs.
Following the container listing are abstracts for most of the cases included in this collection.
Biography
Henry O. Fuchs was professor of mechanical engineering at Stanford University, 1964-1973, and director of the Engineering Case Program.
Provenance
Gift of Henry O. Fuchs, 1981.
Access Restrictions
None.
Engineering -- Case studies.; Photoprints.; Engineering -- Study and teaching.; Stanford University. Engineering Case Program; Fuchs, H. O. (Henry Otten); Arnold, John E., 1913-1963
- Case studies
  - Variable Stability System of the X-14A VTOL Aircraft, J. Hill, G. Kardos, A. Winn, 1970; ECL 162; Total 28 pages: 7 pages text (Parts A&B); 21 pages exhibits
    Scope and Contents note
    The first part of this case describes the original control system and reasons for adding a variable-stability auxiliary system to the Bell X-14 experimental aircraft. By means of excerpts from the original project notebook, the student is provided with the technical requirements of the system. The second part includes the project notebook calculations for the first part and poses the additional problems of writing a preliminary progress report, designing a simulator for the control system, and drawing a block diagram of the control system. A brief instructor's note is available.
  - Development of a Stainless Steel Trashrack, R. J. Shuman, 1970; ECL 161; Total 29 pages: 9 pages text; 20 pages exhibits
    Few people have seen the second largest stainless steel structure in the United States-the trashrack system for the Oroville Dam powerplant. The case details how stainless steel was substituted for mild steel. The substitution had to be justified on a superior function and lower cost basis, leading to a sophisticated analysis of a rather prosaic component. The case is interesting both as a technical achievement and as an example of the way engineering innovations are accomplished.
  - To Find a Bullet, Geza Kardos, 1971; ECL 174; Total 31 pages: 10 pages text, 21 pages exhibits
    This case tells of an unusual application of the engineering method, the location of a missing bullet in a police case. The construction of the case is to show and to lead the student through the solution as carried out by Jorgen Vindum, the principal investigator. The case is divided into three parts: each section ends at a critical decision point and students can be asked to discuss the course of action to be followed. The case involves a mixture of technology, computer application, intuition, experimentation, logical thinking and plain luck. Instructor's Note is available. Parts A, B, C.
  - Negligence, Drew V. Nelson, 1971; ECL 178; Total 65 pages: 57 pages text, 8 pages exhibits.
    A case study concerning a products liability lawsuit which arose out of an industrial accident in which Plaintiff was severely injured while operating a large mechanical press. Emphasis is on engineering aspects of the case, as extracted from depositions of expert witnesses. Important elements of Plaintiff's trial brief, legal arguments, etc. are also presented. Parts A, B, C, D.
  - A Four Barrel Step-and-Repeat Camera, Geza Kardos, 1971; ECL 181; Total 32 pages
    Paul Piper was hired by the Friden Research Center to design, develop and produce a microphotographic camera for the production of final stage integrated circuit masks. Piper's problems are described from the management decision to make instead of to buy the camera through the design to the testing and modifications of the unit. An Instructor's Note is available.
  - The Design of the Bart-AFC Barrier Drive System at IBM, R. Piziali, 1972; ECL 185; Total 53 pages: 35 pages text, 18 pages exhibits
    This case describes in part the design effort and decision process associated with the development of an actuating system at IBM, San Jose. The case starts when delivery is due in 16 months and only an unsatisfactory prototype exists. Parts A, B, C.
  - The Pickup-Head Link Failure, R. Piziali, 1972; ECL 186; Total 27 pages: 12 pages text, 15 pages exhibits
    The IBM 2321 is a vast storage device which reads and writes data on a magnetic strip. These strips are stored in cells and mechanically taken from the cells for read-write operations and then returned. With the 2321 in full production and in the field, the pickup-head link began to fail. After a metallurgical fix of the link failed, stresses due to three independent loads were re-examined.
    Later the link was redesigned, but the pin on the end of the link began to fail. Further redesign involved metallurgical and structural analysis. Parts A, B.
  - Value Engineering Applied to an IBM Leveling Screw, R. Piziali, 1972; ECL 187; Total 19 pages: 9 pages text, 10 pages exhibits
    This case provides a brief look at the methodology of Value Engineering. A leveling screw for the IBM 1311 disk storage drive was assigned to students in an IBM Value Engineering Seminar. The students applied their newly learned techniques to redesign the leveling screw to reduce cost while maintaining function. Their solution was so successful that it was put into production on many IBM systems resulting in over one million dollars in savings.
  - The Stun-Gun, A. P. Shack and G. Kardos, 1972; ECL 188; Total 29 pages: 12 pages text, 17 exhibits.
    Bob Mawhinney recalls the invention and development of a riot-control weapon which shoots a non-lethal spin stabilized bean bag. Part A gives the background feasibility calculations. Part B relates development of a cartridge suitable for military use. Part C shows how a complete system suitable for civilian use was developed.
  - Laser Hardware, Fred Moreno, 1972; ECL 189; Total 56 pages: 32 pages text, 24 pages exhibits
    Fred Moreno, mechanical engineer in Sylvania's Electronic Systems group is assigned to work with the Electro-Optics Organization on devices for satellite laser communication. Work on temperature control and on mirror alignment for the breadboard demonstration model are described in Part A. Part B discusses thermal contact resistance and choice of materials for space vacuum. Part C relates work on the later functional test model, where weight, space, and demonstrated reliability become additional constraints. Part D describes three technical problems: energy for warm-up, vibration resonance, thermal conductance and modulator operating temperature. Part E shows Fred's solutions of these technical problems.
  - The Go-Matic Accessory for Motorcycles, Prem Garg, 1969; ECL 113; Total 23 pages: 10 pages text, 13 pages exhibits
    Go-Matic is a gear shift mechanism which, when installed in place of the final drive sprocket on a lightweight motorcycle, enables the rider to select either of two speed ranges (high, street range or low, trail range) by moving a lever. This case traces the development and marketing history of the device from the point of view of Mr. Neal Williams, President of the Go-Power Corporation, which manufactured it.
  - Design of a Hand Operated Film Drive Mechanism, John Sondeno, 1969; ECL 111; Total 19 pages: 9 pages text, 10 pages exhibits
    This is the story of a mechanical design undertaken by the R. A. Morgan Optical Engineering Company: a microfilm reader-printer was to be modified so that it could accept 105 mm. roll film as well as 105 mm. cut sheets. The task, according to Mr. Morgan, was to design some sort of transmission to manually turn drive shafts for the film spools in a manner that would be convenient to the operator and aeshetically attractive.
  - Development of a Circular Strike Plate at Schlage Lock Company, Richard C. Bourne, 1968; ECL 114; Total 50 pages (Parts A,B,C,D): 21 pages text and 29 pages exhibits
    Most doors are held in a closed position by a system comprised of a retractable latch bolt located in the door edge and a strike plate fastened to the door frame, the plate being cut with a hole to receive the latchbolt. In 1963 Mr. Ernest L. Schlage, Director of Research at the Schlage Lock Company, undertook the design of a new circular strike plate which could be installed with a single boring operation rather than the hand chiseling or routing required with the traditional rectangular strikes. Part A of the case includes background on the components of the Schlage cylindrical lock and design requirements for the new strike. Part B describes the steps taken which resulted in the design and introduction of a circular strike meeting these requirements. Parts C and D deal with the refinement and modicication of Schlage's original design which led to production of an adjustable circular strike.
  - Harvey La Branche: Spring Failures in a New Toy Rifle, Karl H. Vesper, 1968; ECL 120; 26 pages total (parts A and B): 8 text, 18 exhibits
    Mattel Incorporated was about to introduce a new toy rifle which used a recording to produce its cracking sound. Orders for thousands of these rifles had been received and production tooling was underway. Some handmade samples of the guns had been assembled, then cocked and fired over 6,000 times without failure. Then some phosphor bronze clutch springs began to break on the first batch of 100 guns which had been assembled from production parts. Mr. Harvey LaBrance, Director of Product Development Engineering, had to decide on a cure for the problem.
  - Warren Deutsch: Design of a Satellite Controlling Instrument Panel, Mitchel Blanton, 1968; ECL 124; Total 31 pages (Parts A and B); 12 text and 19 exhibits
    Ground control stations are equipped with instrumentation for sending to a satellite commands controlling its functions. Technicians must be able to handle large numbers of such functions (Perhaps 100 for a typical satellite) from a single control panel. To accomplish this task Philco-Ford engineers had designed a device called POK (Page Overlay Keyboard) which consisted of an array of buttons plus overlays, or pages, which could adapt the panel to a variety of functions. Warren Deutsch, head of the Value Engineering Department at Philco-Ford, felt this system was unnecessarily cumbersome and set out to improve on it. Part A of the case describes the problem and Mr. Deutsch's approach to it. Part B deals with refinements of his design.
  - Plastic Pipe Saddle Design, Prem Garg, 1969; ECL 126; Total 43 pages: 9 pages text, 34 pages exhibits.
    Pipe saddles are functionally similar to T-joints. They are used extensively in piping networks for branching off from the main line and can be mounted on existing networks without interrupting the flow in the main line. In 1965 there were no saddles satisfactory for use on plastic pipe which had become increasingly popular for municipal, irrigation, gas and industrial uses. The case describes the design and manufacture of a suitable plastic pipe saddle.
  - Three Years to Design a Door, Drew V. Nelson, 1969; ECL 127; Total 46 pages (A and B): 10 pages text, 36 pages exhibits.
    Part A tells how the Schlage Company started to design a service door for the Hilton Hotel in San Francisco and shows the first two iterations including the patent issued for this design. Part B shows the final design and the end result of this 3 year effort on which about 5,000 man hours of engineering time had been spent. Instructor's Note is available.
  - Design of a Centrifuge Rotor Cap, P. C. Garg, 1969; ECL 137; Total 16 pages: 8 pages text, 8 pages exhibits.
    Mr. Ken Jacobsen, project engineer at the Spinco Division of Beckman Instruments Inc., had proposed to incorporate new features in an ultracentrifuge. These features had been developed in a national laboratory. They now had to be improved and refined for the Spinco production model. Some background on the operation of ultracentrifuges is given; attention is focused on the detail design of a subsystem and on the technical difficulties which Mr. Jacobsen had to surmount to achieve a satisfactory product.
  - Electron Beam Collimator, M. J. Lum, 1969; ECL 138; Total 11 pages: 8 pages, text, 3 pages exhibits.
    Research physicists at Stanford Linear Accelerator Center discovered secondary radiation effects accompanying certain experiments with the electron beam. Because of these effects, the beam's cross section was difficult to define. The scientists asked the Research Area Department at SLAC to design a collimator, an adjustable device to block out the outer portion of the beam allowing only the central beam core to pass through. Dr. Ed. Seppi, head of the Research Area Department, gave the job to Mr. Aaron Baumgarten, who told the case writer how he designed the collimator.
  - A Special Testing Problem at IBM, K. J. Waldron, 1970; ECL 144; Total 24 pages: 8 pages text, 16 pages exhibits.
    Chris Jako was asked to design a machine which would detect oil-canning of computer drum memory reading heads. Oil-canning is caused by small differences in the lengths of six beryllium copper strips. They are mounted between a fixed base and the moving head and serve as springs and conductors. This case can be used to practice elastic stability theory, amplifier circuit design, or electro-mechanical precision design.
  - Howard Ameson's Pool-Sweep, P. C. Garg, 1970; ECL 146; Total 27 pages: 15 pages text, 12 pages exhibits.
    In 1958 Mr. Howard Arneson, rather fortuitously, came across an idea for a device to clean swimming pools automatically. To pursue this idea further, he started a tiny company with $8,000 in 1960. By 1965 the device was in production and in 1969 his company had sales exceeding six million dollars. Mr. Arneson now heads the company he sold to Castle and Cooke Inc. for 9 million dollars in 1969. The case tells Mr. Arneson's story.
  - Design of a Ball Transfer Unit for Air Cargo, R. K. Ganeriwal, 1970; ECL 149; Total 11 pages (Parts A,B,C): 4 pages text, 7 pages exhibits
    Westscope was one of the companies which was requested to quote on a ball transfer unit for the cargo system on the Boeing 747. This case describes the development of a suitable unit at Westscope. The case is written in three parts, each part describing a different phase of the design development.
  - Drop Master, R. Ganeriwal., 1970; ECL 150; Total 23 pages (Part A and B): 11 pages text, 12 pages exhibits.
    Drop Master is a device used for monitoring the rate of fluid administered intravenously. The device was invented and developed at Smith Kline Instruments Inc. After the Drop Master was put on the market, a number of service calls from the customers indicated that the device was too sensitive to temporary flow rate changes. This case describes how the difficulty was overcome.
  - Underwater Pipeline, Dean C. Ing, 1970; ECL 151; Total 20 pages: (Parts A,B,C): 17 pages text, 3 pages exhibits.
    Robert Kinner, a structural analyst, had been loaned to the undersea pipeline project to check the design of pipe bundles which drop down from a height of about 15 feet above the sea floor and are subject to several design constraints. He found that the pipes would buckle unless the design was changed and proposed a feasible design. When the project management doubted Rob's analysis he devised a very quick and inexpensive test to prove his assumptions. Part A outlines the problem. Part B shows Rob's solution. Part C show his tests and the associated calculations. The case is useful in connection with beam bending theory and to show the mechanics of interdepartmental cooperation in a large company.
  - Positioning a Microwave Diode, S. Hayes and R. Ganeriwal, 1970; ECL 156; Total 14 pages: 10 pages text; 4 pages exhibits
    The micro switches for the Apollo antennas had to withstand a temperature range of 140° and high vibration levels during lift-off. The problems and the solutions are described in the case.
  - Interfaces at Sterling Development Laboratories, Sue Hays, 1970; ECL 157; Total 15 pages (Parts A,B,C)
    Sterling Development Laboratories contract was a large one: To build a complete data collection system which included two antennas, two receivers, a transmitter, a data processing display, and recording center. Customer constraints and the nature of the electronic interface between the digital recorder and the computer magnetic tape controller combined to cause difficulties.
  - Jumping a Derrick, Professor Ralph J. Smith, 1970; ECL 159; Total 13 pages: 8 pages text, 5 pages exhibits.
    In this case study in construction engineering, Dan Jeffrey, a young civil engineer, on his first field assignment for the Bethlehem Steel Corporation, explains the decisions he must make in determining the safety of storing steel on a partially completed floor of a new building. Instructor's note is available.
  - Expansion of the Danville Pumping Plant, James C. Collins, 1970; ECL 160; Total 55 pages: 20 pages text, 35 exhibits.
    Increase in water demand and expansion of pump capacity for the Danville-San Ramon area, selection of pumps and reservoir sites, and problems of design constraints are described chronologically from 1959 through 1969 when the new pumps were installed and tested.
  - Switching a Tracking Antenna, Sue Hays, 1968; ECL73; Total 14 pages: 6 pages text, 8 pages exhibits
    In 1963, Philco-Ford's Western Development Laboratories accepted a contract to design and assemble a sixty-foot satellite tracking antenna for the military. Mr. Ed Fish was one of about one hundred engineers in the department that was to design the antenna. His particular section was responsible for the design of the antenna's control system; this case concerns one aspect of that design-the system of push buttons used to switch the antenna from one to another of its four operating modes.
  - Varian Associates, Redesign of a Liquid Nitrogen Container, William S. Chalk, Ivan A. Shirk and Robert B. Thornhill, 1967; ECL 72; 35 pages; 10 graphic exhibits.
    Varian Associates use a liquid nitrogen container made of polystyrene with metal inserts on their cold trap vacuum pumping system. This container gave rise to a number of customer complaints. Paul Hait was assigned the problem and solved it. Part A presents historical background with examples of trouble reports. Part B relates Paul Hait's attack on the problem and its solution. Part C draws conclusions and examines future prospects.
  - Precision Instrument Company, Modification of a Portable Video and Broadband Instrumentation Recorder, Karl H. Vesper and William H. Clemens, 1967; ECL 76; 13 pages; 6 graphic exhibits.
    A team of four engineers are working to modify an existing video tape recorder so that it can be operated without depending on 60 cycle ac. current supply. Manchi Colah is one of the engineers on this team. The case is concerned with the experiments, calculations, and inquiries which he made in order to arrive at a suitable motor to drive the tape of this recorder.
  - Hewlett-Packard VI, Signal Generator Read-Out Design, Karl H. Vesper, Robert Beardmore and Charles Fernald, 1967; ECL 78; 47 pages.
    Anthony Badger's ingenious solution to the problem of packaging an extended instrumentation scale into a small space and keeping it readable is shown in some detail with much interesting background. Seventeen pages of Part A contain mainly background. Sixteen pages of Part B show the first solution with many pages of the notebooks of Anthony Badger and of Peter Rich. This first solution is not satisfactory. Part C explains the final solution in three pages of text and eleven pages of photographs and notes reproduced from Mr. Rich's notebook.
  - Chaparral, Bolt Failure on a Racing Automobile, Henry O. Fuchs and William H. Clemens, 1967; ECL 79; 3 pages of text and 2 pages of exhibits.
    Mr. Jim Hall, designer and driver of the famous Chaparral race car, gave a talk shortly after reports of bolt failures on his car had appeared in the press. He was asked about these bolt failures. His explanation of the failures and of the way he fixed them are given in the case, together with some additional information.
  - Consolidated Dynamics Corporation, Fracture of a Marine Gear Rim, William H. Clemens, 1968; ECL 80
    The rim of a large marine gear breaks during fabrication. Mr. George Reynolds, head of the metallurgical laboratory investigates the failure and prescribes a remedy. Part A describes the problem and Part B shows the steps which Mr. Reynolds and his staff took. Part A consists of 4 pages of text, 7 pages of graphic exhibits and 5 pages of a laboratory report prepared by Mr. Reynolds at Consolidated Dynamics. Part B consists of 1 page of descriptive text and a 13 page laboratory report by Mr. Reynolds with 1 page of microphotographs. A brief instructor's note for this case is available.
  - Design of an Electron Beam Dump at Stanford Linear Accelerator Center, Munir R. El-Saden, 1967; ECL 82; 16 pages: 7 text and 9 exhibits.
    Early in 1964 Dieter R. Walz, a member of the technical staff at SLAC, was placed in charge of developing a beam dump. This device is a heat exchanger capable of absorbing and dissipating the high energy electron beams which must be disposed of at the end of the 2 mile long accelerator. The case describes performance and maintainance requirements for the beam dump and tells how Walz proceeded with his design.
  - Shielding a Toroid Amplifier at Stanford Linear Accelerator Center, Sue Hays, 1967; ECL 90; Total 8 pages
    Scientists at the Stanford Linear Accelerator Center planned to mount a field strength detecting device inside the pipe through which the electron beam travels. The signal from this device would be passed through an amplifier mounted on the outside of the pipe, then transmitted to a remote oscilloscope. This brief case study describes the design and construction of a shield used to protect the amplifier from stray electromagnetic fields produced by power sources for the accelerator. Included as exhibits are the chassis layout and cover assembly drawings prepared by Pete Demos, the designer assigned to the job.
  - Girder Alignment at Stanford Linear Accelerator Center, Henry O. Fuchs and Sue Hays, 1968; ECL 91; Total 21 pages; 12 text, 9 graphic exhibits.
    The alignment within 1/8 inch of the two mile long Stanford Linear Accelerator presents problems in metrology and in structures. These are explained in part A. Part B is concerned with one of the details: the interconnection and support of the 250 girders which carry the support tube. This interconnection permits adjustment of the alignment if it should ever be disturbed. Detail drawings of parts which connect the girders are shown as originally made and as revised to conform with better drawing practices.
  - Development of a New Drill Steel at Ingersoll-Rand Company, H. O. Fuchs and Ronald J. Shuman, 1967; ECL 94; Total 20 pages, including text, drawings, material specifications, and a patent application.